So we're going to talk about global state management with Pinya.
Pinya, if you don't know,
I believe is French for pineapple and basically it is a successor to Vuex.
So if you've heard from the React community about
Redux pattern and those kind of thing,
Pinya is the evolution of that because Vue did
take inspiration from like the Redux pattern and so we had Vuex for a very long time.
But there were some ergonomics with it that made it kind of tricky to work with over the long period of time.
So Pinya with the Composition API has basically been the evolution of Vuex.
Okay. So in terms of Pinya,
let's take a look at what that looks like.
Because global state management typically is a fairly complicated topic.
So first of all, be sure to pin their docs pinya.vuejs.org.
Once again, this is an officially supported Vue library.
It's got this cute little mascot which I need to get some stickers of.
Basically, Pinya, funny enough,
was started out as just like an experiment that Eduardo,
also known as Postva, who actually wrote VueRouter,
was kind of experimenting with how we might reinvent Vuex.
So he came up with this idea and it's gained a lot of popularity
and thus it is now the official one.
Okay. So to show it in action,
what we're going to go ahead and do is on the playground,
I'm going to go ahead and just install it right now.
So NPM install Pinya.
So once again, let's go and see how we know that we're using it.
We can go ahead and look inside of the package.json.
As we see here, we'll see VueRouter and we see Pinya now.
Now, the only thing we need to do before we need to continue using it though,
it's just like the router,
we need to tell Vue that we're using this plugin basically.
So inside of our main.ts,
we get the opportunity to now create basically a Pinya instance.
How does that work?
It's just like VueRouter actually.
So we can import create Pinya from Pinya.
So just to show you that again,
this time it'll actually auto-complete, there you go.
Now that's right.
So remember that multi-line thing I was telling you about?
This is where this is super helpful because we can say const Pinya equals create Pinya.
Then after that, after we use the router,
we can just say app.usePinya. There you go.
Just like that, you have Pinya enabled on your app.
So how does Pinya actually work?
Creating stores and stuff, this is stuff again,
is typically very complicated.
But I think I've set you all up to see what it's actually like.
What we're going to do is we're going to create a folder called stores.
Because after all, what are we trying to track?
We're trying to track stores of data.
So what are we creating? We're creating a directory for stores.
Why? Because when it comes to global state management,
we're typically referred to as stores of the data,
of the actions we need to take in order to make changes to those data stores.
So let's go ahead and inside of this playground this time.
We noticed that we have this count store over here.
Let's go ahead and recreate this over here.
So I'm going to do count store,
and I'm just going to do it in Pascal case just to make it look different.
What does that look like now inside of Pinya?
Well, let's go ahead and define the store.
As we look at the docs here,
we're going to do things very composition API like.
We're going to import define store from Pinya.
Then what we're going to do then is export a const of use
whatever the count store or whatever the store name is.
So use count store is typically what it's called.
So use, append it to this,
and then we call the define store in here.
Now the difference is one,
we first start by defining how we want the store to be labeled.
So I usually just call it count store,
like whatever it's already called inside of the file name.
Then after that, you get an object that you get to configure.
Inside of here, it's going to look familiar.
So one, you get a state option to return data,
there is a getters option,
and there is an actions option.
So you might think, this looks familiar,
this looks a little bit like options,
and it does in the sense that it's providing you
structure at how you manage your state.
Because what we saw with composition API earlier is that
you can wrangle together whatever you want.
But this, especially when we think about global source,
it's actually useful to have a convention for everyone to follow.
Because you don't really want it to be like the Wild Wild West
when it comes to people managing and accessing data.
Something else that you might notice too though,
missing from here, especially for my fellow VUX users,
there are no mutations.
That is probably one of the best things about Pinya,
is that when we have something in here, like count zero,
and we want to increment the count,
all we got to do is go this.count++,
and it takes care of everything for you.
No more creating this separate thing that's like a mutation
that requires you to call an action,
and then the mutation is basically redundant
of the thing that you're trying to do.
That's all gone.
And so we think of this another way to alias it,
just to provide the mental model,
data computed methods.
That's what you have.
And so if we compare this over now to the counselor
that we originally sort of scaffolded ourselves together
inside of the composables,
you'll see here how different the code is
in the sense that this is just kind of
however I feel like and however I chose to write it.
But you get an additional benefit actually
that I'll show you in right here.
So let's say, let's add that increment amount to 80,
and then this one is gonna be plus equal this
that increment amount,
because this should look familiar
to our base counter stuff that we've done before.
And then we'll have a double count here
that will be a function that receives the state
as an argument,
and we can just return state.count times two,
just like that.
And then I mess something up
because I use the comma instead of a period, boom.
Okay, how is this any different than what we just did?
So we have this right here,
and I'm gonna leave this to the right
so that we have this as a reference.
Now, inside of our base counter this time,
what I'm gonna do is we're gonna go ahead
and actually import this store.
So import useCounterStore or useCountStore, it looks like.
There you go, it actually detected it properly.
So we were getting some type auto completion,
which is super nice.
And this time we'll do a const newCountStore,
which will be the useCountStore like this.
Just like that.
And then we're gonna return newCountStore, just like that.
Okay, so what do we get out of this?
One, I'm gonna show you what it looks like
when we actually use it.
So let me bring that back over here, this is great.
Okay, so first thing first is that
now that you have yourCountStore,
what you actually end up finding out
is that when we look at something like thirdCounterVersion,
so when we look inside of here,
you're gonna notice that we get auto completion here.
It actually can detect properties on that store now.
So you get a lot of auto completion out of this.
So in other words, if you take a look,
increment is actually sitting right here.
It actually knows that it's a property now.
And so there's a lot of work being done
underneath to help with the intelligence
of what's going on when you're managing your code.
And so here we can do count, for example,
and then as you can see, it's zero,
but actually very easily, if we added a button,
we can just say newCountStore.increment.
And then new increment,
and then you can see it just works.
And the reason why I kind of prefaced this
with how global stores are normally complicated,
this should actually remind you of the composable
we kind of designed ourselves.
You have this thing called countStore.
Again, it learns from the options API.
It takes the advantage of the option API
by providing some structure,
gives you the chance to manipulate it as you see fit,
but then when you call it, it feels just as natural
as using any other part of the data.
Whereas in a lot of other state managements
that I've used before, there's usually a lot
in terms of going in to fetch a certain thing
and then auto completion becomes a bit of a pain.
If you use Vuex, you knew that you had to type the string
exactly a certain way to initiate a certain action.
There was a lot of opportunities for mistakes.
But with this, it's easy for us to understand
what's happening, and on top of that,
I'm always a big fan of conventions,
especially when it comes to debugging.
We know that state management is notoriously difficult to do.
And so, if you take a look right here,
you'll notice that another benefit you get by using Pinya
is that you get this dev tool right here.
And we can actually go ahead and start inspecting it
and doing stuff just like you normally would want to do
when you're debugging a large application.
And the other thing that, again,
it feels really natural as we do this right now,
is that unlike a global state management store
like the way Vuex used to be,
you used to have to intentionally name space modules.
In other words, you have to be like,
from this global piece, only take this small piece
and import it here.
Only take this small piece and import it here.
But then sometimes you still ended up with like,
importing everything at once, right?
So Vuex stores became rather cumbersome
and people had trouble with that.
But with this new model of like a composable about Pinya,
this is actually modular by default.
You only import the stores you need where you need them.
And so almost without even thinking about it,
you saw the performance bottleneck
that might have naturally occurred
in an enterprise grade app where you have the single,
the singleton tracking global state,
everyone just chucking stuff in there because they can
or it's the easiest thing to do.
But now it almost is just as easy to go,
wait, my functionality is about login.
I'm gonna create a login store.
I'm not gonna toss it in the global state.
I'm gonna actually think of it modular first.
And the fact that it's named states modular first,
I think that's wonderful because it encourages us
to use best practices without even realizing it.
And that's some of the best sort of advancements
that we can have when it comes to developer toys.